Boker tov, today is the last daf of נזיר nazir, *Nazir* ס"ו
*Samech Vav* and we pick up with the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* at
the bottom of ס"ה עמוד ב' *Samech Heh Amud Bet*. And we
had just
had a משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* that really had very little to do
with נזיר nazir, *Nazir* except that it had the phrase רגלים לדבר
raglayim ladavar. *Raglayim L'davar*, which was a phrase we had at the
beginning of the פרק *Perek*, and it was about checking a זב
zav *Zav* to make sure that the flow was not due to
some external cause, but once that was before he became a זב
zav, *Zav*, but once he became a זב zav *Zav* he had
two flows,
then additional flows which are relevant because a third one means he
brings a קרבן *Korban*, and if he's trying to get his seven
days without flow, a flow would mean he would have to start
again, then those types of cases we're not concerned with external causes
or the possibility of external causes because of רגלים לדבר raglayim ladavar.
*Raglayim L'davar*, because once he's already a זב zav *Zav* we assume
that the continued flow is as a result of that זיבה ziva,
*Ziva*, of that condition and not due to something external. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now says, the beginning of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
after the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*, six lines from the bottom, מנא הני
מילי *Minani Milli*? Where do you get this from? So that this
idea that we make this distinction between external causes? אמר רבי נתן
אמר קרא *Amar Rabbi Natan Amar Kra*: והזב את זובו *V'hazav et
zovo*. The flow, the one who has the flow of the flow.
ראייה re'iyah שלישית *Re'iyah shelishit* היקש *hikeish* לנקבה *l'nekeivah*. So the end
of the פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* is והזב את זובו לזכר ולנקבה *V'hazav
et zovo l'zachar ul'nekeivah*,
and the one who flows the flow, whether male or female. So
there's a woman who's a זבה zavah *Zava*. Now for a woman
the difference between the basic difference in the תורה *Torah* is between
something that is natural and not natural, or not regular. So for
a woman it's a difference between a נדה *Niddah*, bleeding during her
menstrual period, and a זבה *Zava*, bleeding not during her menstrual period.
So for her it's all about bleeding, not a question about what
is flowing, but it's about when is it flowing. For the man
it's a difference between a seminal emission, שכבת זרע shichvat zera. *Shichvat
Zera*, which is natural, and זיבה ziva *Ziva*, which is not a
question about the time that it's occurring, but what actually is being
emitted, something that is not semen, something that is considered זיבה ziva
*Ziva* based on, and there's ways that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* talks
about or the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* talks about what exactly that looks
like in terms of the actual consistency of the thing that is
flowing. Okay, so both of them you have the natural sort of
condition and the not natural condition.
Now by a woman, we learn from elsewhere that whether the blood
is coming out because of what you would even if the blood
is coming out due to אונס onus, *ones*, some external cause, actually
some of the cases exactly mentioned in the משנה mishna *Mishnah*, whether
we think that maybe it's due to something she ate or actually
the case about she exertion or she jumped up and down, whatever
it is, it doesn't matter whether that's due to some external cause,
אונס onus, *ones* doesn't matter. So for the man though, we say
that it does if it's based on an external cause. So where
do we get this from? So because it says והזב את זובו
*V'hazav et zovo*, and זובו *zovo* is there like masculine, and then
לזכר ולנקבה *l'zachar ul'nekeivah*. So when is male like the female that
external causes don't matter? After והזב את זובו *V'hazav et zovo*. If
there's been already two flows, the double language of the word זוב
*zov*, then if continued flows are due to אונס onus *ones*, it
doesn't matter, like by a woman where it never matters. Okay, so
ראייה re'iyah שלישית *Re'iyah shelishit* היקש *hikeish* לנקבה *l'nekeivah*. Starting by the
third sighting of the flow, then it's like a woman that it
does not matter even due to external causes. So גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says ותניא *v'tanya*, but don't we teach in a ברייתא braita, *Baraita*,
רבי אליעזר אומר omer בשלישית בודקין אותו ברביעית אין בודקין אותו *Rabbi
Eliezer omer bishlishit bodkin oto birvi'it ein bodkin oto*, that even for
the third flow, you see whether there are external causes and if
so it's discounted, and he would not have to bring a קרבן
*Korban*. He would need all three flows to be based on non-external
causes. It's only the fourth flow that that doesn't matter. What's the
relevance of a fourth flow? As I've been saying, that then he
tries to get seven days of non-flow, and there if it is
a flow due to an external cause during that seven clean days,
then we don't care. But for even the third flow we do
care according to רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*. So what's that based on?
אלא ela... באת קמיפלגי *Ela b'et kamifligi*. Fine, so for him it's
based on the extra word את *et*. רבי אליעזר דריש את ורבנן
לא דרשי את *Rabbi Eliezer darish et v'rabbanan lo darshi et*, right,
והזב את זובו *V'hazav et zovo*. All right, so do you read
it והזב זובו *V'hazav zovo*, two ראיות *re'iyot* and then afterwards even
due to אונס onus *ones*, it would still be considered a flow,
or do you read it והזב את זובו *V'hazav et zovo*, three
ראיות *re'iyot* and then afterwards?
All right, isn't that the same as hermeneutic, right?
That's רב Rav נחום איש גמזו *Rav Nachum Ish Gamzu*, all of
that fun stuff, exactly, right. Okay, so basically again, for זב zav,
*Zav* the first two to three ראיות *re'iyot* based on this debate,
it's only a problem if it's you check to make sure there
are no external causes, if there might be external causes it's not
a problem, but starting either on the third ראייה *re'iyah* that obligates
him in a קרבן *Korban* or the ראייה *re'iyah* afterwards which could
come to prevent him from getting his period of seven clean days,
in those cases it does not matter due to an external cause.
And the debate is whether
it's. Everybody agrees from the fourth on it does not matter. Okay,
so that's that first principle that we only check for external causes
during those initial ראיות. Now it goes on, אונס וספקו. onus vesfeko.
אמר
רבא: Amar Rava: So now the next line of the משנה mishna.
is a little bit unclear. Something due to an אונס, oness, external
cause, and a ספק, safek, doubt, and semen are טמאים. teme'im. Now
we get אונס, אונס was what we just said, after two flows,
maybe three, even due to external causes, it's still a problem. That's
what אונס is. What is ספקו sfeko and שכבת זרעו? shichvat zaro?
And שכבת זרעו shichvat zaro seems pretty clear, semen, but semen of
a זב zav is not a problem per se. So we'll worry
about שכבת זרעו shichvat zaro in a minute, but what's this ספק
safek issue? So let's take a look. אמר רבא: Amar Rava: לא
תימא ספק חזה ספק לא חזה אלא ודאי חזה ספק מחמת שכבת
זרע ספק מחמת ראייה. lo teima sfek chaza sfek lo chaza ela
vadai chaza sfek machmat shichvat zera sfek machmat re'iah. So don't say
that the issue of the משנה mishna. if there's a doubt we
assume he is טמא tamei after he has had two or three
flows, let's say two, is that you don't know if he had
any if anything came out at all. Because that would not say
רגליים לדבר, raglayim ladavar, just because this guy has this condition doesn't
mean that if you don't know if anything came out that you
assume something came out, right? Even if it's even if he had
two or three times, doesn't mean, oh well we don't know, let's
just assume that it happened again. No, no, no. It means something
did come out, you just don't know its identity. Now what's the
issue about not knowing its identity? So he says you don't know
if it was a result, I mean, if it was a result
of seminal emission or not. Why does that matter? Because if you
take a look, תוספות Tosafot clarifies, תוספות Tosafot says like this:
פירוש ר"י, Peirush Ri, the תוספות, Tosafot, אמר רבא, Amar Rava, top
of the דף: daf: חדינן בפרק קמא פלך. chadinan bepereq Kama Pelekh.
זיבה דפתיכא בי שכבת זרע לא סתרה אלא יום אחד. זיבה דלא
פתיכא בי שכבת זרע סתרה שבעה. ziva depeticha bei shichvat zera lo
satra ela yom echad. ziva delo peticha bei shichvat zera satra shiva.
Okay, so this is again this little obscure הלכה halachah which is
if this flow comes out together mixed in with semen, then it
only destroys one day. If it's not, it destroys all seven. And
guy's been counting days of no flow. He's up to day three,
okay, for example. And then he has some and then something happened.
So if he just has a seminal emission, doesn't do anything, that's
not זיבה, ziva that doesn't interrupt. Let's say however it's a seminal
emission that has with it some of this other זיבה ziva liquid,
the fluid mixed in with it. Then he can't count that one
day, okay, but he can still keep on counting. So if today
was day three, he has two days before, today doesn't count, but
then he goes tomorrow, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. He just can't
count that one day. If however it is a זיבה ziva that
is coming out without any semen, just by itself, then he has
to start all over again from the beginning.
So it's an analogous or parallel to the question of whether the
blood is from the uterine lining or from some other source?
Yeah, so there is some analogy there although again, I mean, there
is some analogy although here what is different is that here even
though we know the זיבה ziva. is coming out, if it's not
coming out by itself, it has a different impact on his status.
But yeah, there are all these interesting parallels between that and a
זבה who is getting seven clean days as well. Okay, but so
the point for us is, so we need to know whether his
זיבה ziva came out by itself or together with semen. So the
question is, does he now have to start the seven days all
over again or does he just lose this day? That's the ספק.
safek. Okay, so the example would be, תוספות Tosafot says, he finds
on let's say his underwear, he finds stains of both, and he
doesn't know, did they come out separately or did they come out
together? So in that case because he's already a זב, zav that's
the רגליים לדבר raglayim ladavar of the משנה, mishna. you assume that,
you know, you make the more חומרא chumra read of what happened
and you assume that the זיבה ziva. came out by itself and
he has to start all over again rather than it came out
mixed together with the שכבת זרע.
shichvat zera, What is פתיכא, peticha, what is פתיכא? peticha?
Mixed in. Okay, mixed, yeah.
So so like intertwined is more like whatever. Okay, so anyway, but
that's a little not the right image. Okay, so אלא ודאי חזה,
ela vadai chaza, back to the גמרא, Gemara he definitely saw, ספק
מחמת שכבת זרע, sfek machmat shichvat zera, it's a doubt whether it
came as a result of the שכבת זרע, shikhvat zera ספק מחמת
ראייה, sfek machmat re'iah, or whether it came by itself. That's the
way תוספות Tosafot is reading it. כיון שנזקק לטומאה, keivan shenizkak letumah,
now that he's already seen twice or three times, ספקו טמא, sfeko
tamei, we'll assume the worst and we'll assume it came out by
itself and he has to start all seven days again. Okay, so
that's the ספקו. sfeko. Now what's the last one, שכבת זרעו, shichvat
zaro, the semen? Because semen by itself of a זב zav, does
not affect his status. So what does that mean? טמאה. teme'ah. So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara. says. למאי הלכתא? lemai hilchata? For
what הלכה halachah is this or למאי, lemai, for what is this?
אילימא למגע, ileima lemaga, if it is to tell you that if
you touch the semen you're טמא, tamei, okay, big deal. מי גרע
שכבת זרע דטהור? mi gara shichvat zera detahor? The semen of a
normal person who is טהור, tahor, of any normal man, it's considered
the semen is an אב הטומאה av hatumah and somebody who touches
it is טמא. tamei. So obviously we mean something more than that.
אלא זרעו של זב מטמא במשא. ela zaro shel zav metamei bemasa.
So what we must be saying is that his semen is considered
to have the same weight as his זיבה. ziva which is that
you're טמא tamei not just by touching it, but even by carrying
it. Okay, the flow, the זיבה ziva. of a זב zav, causes
טומאה tumah even by being carried, okay, even not being touched. So
now we're going to say that once he's a זב, zav. even
his semen has the same status. So now we're going to question
that, why should we say such a thing, his semen is not
זיבה. ziva Okay,
מאן שמעת ליה דאמר שכבת זרעו של זב מטמא במשא. Man sham'at
leh d'amar shikhvat zar'o shel zav mitamei b'massa. Now who is the
one that says that, that the semen of a זב zav, is
treated like the זיבה ziva. itself and causes טומאה tumah by being
carried? אילימא האי תנא דתניא, Ileima hai tanna d'tanya, if it's the
following תנא, tanna, which we taught in a ברייתא, beraita. רבי אליעזר
אומר שכבת זרעו של זב אינו מטמא
במשא, Rabbi Eliezer omer shikhvat zar'o shel zav eino mitamei b'massa, that
the semen is not מטמא mitamei by being carried. רבי יהושע אומר
מטמא במשא, Rabbi Yehoshua omer mitamei b'massa, no if it's from a
זב zav, it is מטמא mitamei by being carried. לפי שאי אפשר
לבוא לא צחצוחי זיבה, Lefi she'efshar l'vo lo tzikhtzukhei ziva,
not because in principle semen has that status. No, but because once
this guy is a זב, zav. we assume that anything that's coming
out, any penile emission, any semen is going to have in it
some drops of this other flow, of this זיבה. ziva So that's
why. All right, so obviously so maybe our משנה mishna, is רבי
יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, that would make sense. Once he's a זב, zav,
we're going to רגליים לדבר raglayim ladavar and you'll assume that any
emission, even if it looks like seminal emission, has some זיבה ziva.
in it and you'll be strict. Okay, אפילו רבי יהושע, Afilu Rabbi
Yehoshua,
but now the גמרא Gemara says wait a minute, אפילו רבי יהושע
לא אמר אלא משום צחצוחי זיבה. Afilu Rabbi Yehoshua lo amar ella
mishum tzikhtzukhei ziva. He only says it because of the little droplets
of זיבה. ziva. אבל בעיניה לא אמר, Aval be'inei lo amar, he
would not say the semen just purely by itself would be a
problem. Now it's still a funny pushback because it's a very reasonable
read of the משנה. Mishnah, His semen you treat strictly because of
רגליים לדבר, raglayim ladavar, because you assume there's other stuff in it.
End of story, right? According to him there's no way you're going
to get it pure. What are you going to do, run it
through a centrifuge or whatever, I mean? Obviously there's no way to,
we're not talking abstractly, we're looking in practice. In practice his שכבת
זרע shikhvat zera is a problem because he's already a זב.
zav, But anyway, but dried liquid and as it's dried sweat or
whatever? Right, exactly. Anything that has dried already on the upholstery of
the...
Yeah, the dried would... I mean there is some, yeah, that's correct,
I mean actually we're going to get in a minute to a
question about that but for now let's say yes. Okay, so it's
actually no, we're not going to get to that here, I'm sorry.
Anyway, but as a general rule I'll say yes. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says אפילו הכי אלא משום צחצוחי זיבה אבל בעיניה לא.
Afilu hachi ella mishum tzikhtzukhei ziva aval be'inei lo. אלא אמר רב
אדא בר אהבה לומר שאין תולין בה. Ella amar Rav Ada bar
Ahava lomar she'ein tolin bah. You do not sort of attribute it
to it. What does that mean? It means that remember we had
these things that you said 'oh, if the זיבה ziva comes due
to an external cause, it's not really considered a זיבה.' ziva. So
one of an external cause would be a man just had an
ejaculate, had a seminal emission, and then afterwards he had a flow,
he had a זיבה. zivah So in that case you would say
that that זיבה zivah is due to some external cause, due to
you know the fact that maybe his body now has been weakened
through this or you know somehow has it had this other experience
right before that led to this flow that followed it and it's
not therefore that's considered an external cause, an אונס, and it would
not be considered a זיבה. zivah, All right, like the other external
causes in our משנה. Mishnah, Okay, so if he's saying let's say
that happened after the guy had two flows. After he had two
flows then he became a בעל קרי, ba'al keri, he had a
seminal emission, and then he had another flow. So you want to
say, 'ah, discount that other flow, it's coming after seminal emission.' The
same way you don't say that by the other external causes in
the משנה. Mishnah Once he is already a זב, zav, you don't
care about these external causes. Okay, so that's how he's reading the
שכבת זרע shikhvat zera. is not פשט. pshat. I think the פשט
pshat was very good beforehand, but okay, that's what the גמרא Gemara
says now. אלא אמר רב אדא בר אהבה לומר שאין
תולין בה. Ella amar Rav Ada bar Ahava lomar she'ein tolin bah.
Okay, like you don't attribute the flow to other causes, you don't
attribute it to this.
But if he was a זב, zav if he was a זב.
zav.
No, if he was not a זב, zav then then you would
be תולה בה. toleh bah. If he were not a זב, zav
the same way if he had had certain types of food or
exerted himself or was sick, and then he had a flow, it
would not be a flow that would be a problem because it
was due to external causes. If he had a seminal emission and
then he had a flow it would not be a problem. But
now that he's already a זב, zav then the flow that comes
after these causes is a problem.
Okay. And you don't, right, you do not sort of, you know,
dismiss it, like, you know, attribute it and dismiss it due to
the שכבת זרע. shichvat zera Okay, so סבר פפא קמיה דרבא למימר
איידי חולשא הוא דחזי. Savar Pappa kamei deRava lomeimar aidi khulsha hu
dekhazei. So the reason that we would normally say that a flow
after seminal emission is not a problem, you know, if it came
at the outset, not during, is because it's due to the weakness,
the body is feeling a little more, you know, depleted and therefore
that's why it happened and that's sort of like coming due to
illness and coming due to an external cause. That's why. So it's
because of the physical reality of it. אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei
Rava, so רבא Rava challenged this, that this is why, again, it's
okay now in an explanation of the משנה, Mishnah but now we're
just discussing this idea why. Why is it that at the outset
we, if it comes after seminal emission, it’s not a problem? So
we’re just saying because physically the reality of the body.
אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei Rava, so Rava says that can’t be.
ותנן, V'atnan, we saw in the משנה, Mishnah גר שנתגייר, ger shenitgayer,
a person converted. מטמא מיד בזיבה, metamei miyad bezivah, and then he
has a flow, he becomes a זב zav right away. And we
don’t care if a minute before he converted, let’s say he had
a seminal emission. That’s the way he’s reading it, we don’t care
about his past history. Okay, now why is it? If it’s just
based on the physical state of his body, so we should be
concerned about what happened to him even before he went to the
מקוה mikvah and became a גר. ger. Right, if that’s the state
of his body, that’s the state of his body. Now of course
question is who said we’re talking about a special case like that?
I mean you have all these other cases in the משנה, Mishnah,
let’s say he ate something, let’s say he was sick, presumably those
would continue to be factors even after he converted. But for some
reason we’re saying, no, the משנה Mishnah. doesn’t distinguish, even if he
had a seminal emission right before he converted, he would still be
a זב. zav. So you see it’s not based on what that
does to the physical state of his body. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says, אמר ליה, amar lei, אין לך חולי גדול מזה. ein
lecha choli gadol mizeh. You don’t have an illness greater than this.
Now that doesn’t sound like that’s a retort back. What does that
mean? You don’t have an illness greater than this. What, converting is
an illness? So let’s see what תוספות Tosafot says. Look at תוספות,
Tosafot, אמר ליה רבא והתנן, Amar lei Rava v’hatnan, you see the
תוספות Tosafot אמר רבא, amar Rava, it’s like five lines, four lines
from the bottom of the
page. והתנן גר שנתגייר מטמא בזיבה מיד. V’hatnan ger shenitgayer metamei bezivah
miyad. הכי גרסינן, Hachi garsinan, ואמאי, v’amai, this is not a retort
back, this is part of Rava’s question. האין לך חולי גדול מזה.
Ha’ein lecha choli gadol mizeh. פירוש ר"י, Peirush Ri, גר שראה קרי
קודם שנתגייר, ger she’ra’ah keri kodem shenitgayer, that’s what we’re just assuming
the case is. Why we’re assuming that I don’t know. ונתגייר וראה
זיבה, U’nitgayer vera’ah zivah, מטמא בזיבה. metamei bezivah. ולא תפטור קרי את
הזיבה, V’lo tiftor keri et hazivah, and we don’t say that the
fact that he had this right before he converted
is a factor. ואם כדברי רב אדא בר רב פפא, V’im kedivrei
Rav Adda bar Rav Pappa, לטעמיה דקרי פוטר זיבה הבאה אחריו משום
חולשא, l’teimei d’keri potar zivah haba achrav mishum chulsha, I think it’s
just because of the state of the body, its weakness.
So גבי גר נמי נימא הכי, gabei ger nami neima hachi, דאין
לך חולי גדול מזה, d’ein lecha choli gadol mizeh, meaning דכי היכי,
d’chi heichi, meaning the same way if he had that condition before
he converted, that’s also relevant here. Again, it doesn’t really fit the
words אין לך חולי גדול מזה, ein lecha choli gadol mizeh, even
the way תוספות Tosafot is reading it with switching the גירסא, girsa,
it’s just saying that שכבת זרע shichvat zera, is the same reality
in this case as well, not there’s nothing greater than this. It’s
saying in this case when he converted, it should be the same
reality, it should be the same condition.
It’s a tremendous difference, one minute he wasn't Jewish, then the next
minute he was Jewish, in between,
yeah, but that’s not how תוספות Tosafot is reading it. He says
דכי היכי דבדקינן ליה לפטור בקרי, d’chi heichi debatkinan lei liftor bekeri,
דמה לי קרי שראה כשהוא עובד כוכבים, d’mali keri she’ra’ah keshu oved
kochavim, דמה לי שראה כשהוא ישראל. d’mali she’ra’ah keshu Yisrael. It’s not
אין לך חולי גדול מזה, ein lecha choli gadol mizeh, it’s that
this case should be ומאי שנא u’mai shna should really be the
difference. This case should be no different than having had it after
you
converted if it’s the effect on your body. Why should it matter
that it happened before you converted? Again, it’s reading a lot into
this משנה mishnah because the משנה mishnah, did not say that this
condition happened to the guy before he converted. And also it’s like
a real re-read of this phrase אין לך חולי גדול מזה. ein
lecha choli gadol mizeh. Anyway, that’s how תוספות Tosafot reads the גמרא.
Gemara Rava says it can’t be the effect on the body because
then it should be a factor even if it happened before somebody
converted. And it’s not a factor if it happened before you converted.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא תנאי היא, ela tenai hi, really
this is an issue about the תנאים, tanna’im, the status of the
שכבת זרע, shichvat zera meaning what תוספות Tosafot sort of reads in
is the reason that being a זב zav after בעל קרי ba’al
keri is not a problem at the outset, that’s like a special
גזירת הכתוב gzeirat hakatuv which תוספות Tosafot quotes from another מדרש הלכה
midrash halacha that learns it out. And therefore it’s only relevant if
it happens once the guy had converted. It’s not because of the
impact on the body. It was not noticed, for example, in the
list of the seven things that you check for external factors. So
in our משנה, mishnah the seven things you check for external factors
are real physical conditions and presumably even if those things happened before
a guy converted they would be relevant because they’re realities about the
physical impact on the body. The הלכה halachah that having a זיבה
ziva following a בעל, ba’al, following a seminal emission, that that זיבה
ziva, is not counted as a זיבה, ziva that's more of a
גזירת הכתוב gzeirat hakatuv that's not based on the physical condition, and
therefore it only is to happen if the person became a בעל
קרי ba’al keri after he converted. What happened before he converted is
irrelevant. Okay, so that’s in terms of this issue of a זב
zav, following being a בעל קרי. ba’al keri.
So the פסוקים pesukim don’t apply to him because he wasn’t Jewish.
Exactly. Okay, so that’s that issue. Now back to the case of
our משנה. Mishna What does it mean that once he’s a זב
zav his שכבת זרע shichvas zera is טמא? tamei? So let’s take
a look because now if the idea about being a בעל קרי
ba'al keri gets you off of being a זב zav. is a
גזירת הכתוב, gzeirat hakatuv, then maybe it applies even after the guy’s
a זב. zav Remember, the things that we said... The things that
we said change after the guy's a זב zav is because of
רגלים לדבר. raglayim ladavar, And now that we know that this guy's
a זב, zav. we don't attribute it to other factors. We assume
it's from his condition. And if there was a doubt, right, remember
that other case, whether it came with the semen or not the
semen, we assume with the זב zav, probably it came by itself
from its own. All of those are based on certain assumptions of
the physical reality of what's going on here, right? But now that
we're saying that the זיבה ziva following a בעל קרי ba'al keri
is a גזירת הכתוב gezeras hakasuv that it doesn't count as זיבה,
ziva. then presumably that might apply even after the guy's a זב.
zav, So now we have to go back and find the meaning
of the משנה Mishna, by that the שכבת זרע shichvas zera is
not a problem. So let's- I mean, is a problem. Let's take
a look. So it says like this: אלא תנאי היא, ella tanai
hi, it's a debate of תנאים, tana'im, דתניא תנו רבנן. detanya tanu
rabbanan. שכבת זרע של shel זב zav מטמא במשא כל מעת לעת.
metamei bemasa kol me'es le'es. רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi Yosei omer יומו.
yomo. So actually it is- there is an opinion that the semen
causes טומאה tumah 24 hours, if it occurs within 24 hours after
the flow. So the guy had a flow Tuesday at 1:00 PM.
Until Wednesday at 1:00 PM, any semen will be considered to have
the same טומאה tumah as the זיבה ziva. itself. For 24 hours
after the emission, the semen will have the same טומאה, tumah, will
be- even through being carried. And רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says no,
only on the day itself, not on the following day. It won't
go for 24 hours. במאי קמיפלגי? Bemai kamifligi? What's the debate? דשמואל
רמי. DeShmuel rami. שמואל Shmuel showed a contradiction. כתיב: Kesiv: כי יהיה
בך איש אשר לא יהיה טהור מקרה לילה. ki yihyeh becha ish
asher lo yihyeh tahor mikreh layla. Okay, a man will not be
טהור, tahor, an occurrence of the night, this meaning that he has
a seminal emission. Okay, וכתיב לפנות ערב ירחץ במים. uchesiv lifnos erev
yirchatz bamayim. And come evening, he'll bathe in water. He'll be טהור.
tahor. So the way we're reading it is: לא יהיה טהור lo
yihyeh tahor does not mean he is not טהור tahor because he
had a seminal emission. The way we are reading it is, this
is just פסוקים psukim here, it's totally not about a זב zav
at all, you see it's in דברים, Devarim, it's not in תזריע-מצורע,
it's totally about seminal emission. But we're reading it the following way:
לא יהיה טהור, lo yihyeh tahor, he's not טהור tahor for another
reason. He's a זב. zav Okay. So it's, if a man is
already a זב, zav לא יהיה טהור, lo yihyeh tahor, and he
has a seminal emission, he's had a מקרה לילה, mikreh layla, we
treat that as זיבה ziva. as well. Okay, so it's pretty funny.
There's a פרשה parsha that's like two ספרים, sefarim, you know, it's
in דברים, Devarim, after- after it ever mentioned זב, but we're reading
זב into this פרשה. parsha. Okay, why not? So if he is
a זב and he has something at night, then that's also treated
as זיבה. ziva.
And the syntax of the פסוק pasuk is strange, right? כי יהיה
בך
ki
yihyeh
becha asher lo- מקרה לילה mikreh layla אשר לא יהיה טהור. asher
lo yihyeh tahor.
I understand, whatever, okay, right, it's funny that it's first called לא
טהור lo tahor before it describes that he had the emission. So
that's where we're saying, he was already לא טהור. lo tahor. Okay.
So there it says מקרה לילה, mikreh layla, if something happened at
night, meaning the night of the- let's say the seminal emission, right?
So therefore it's going to be treated as זיבה. ziva But another
פסוק pasuk, says, or the end- not the other פסוק, pasuk the
end of the פסוק pasuk, says: והיה לפנות ערב ירחץ במים, vehaya
lifnos erev yirchatz bamayim, towards evening he shall bathe in water, which
means all the way through to the next evening there we would
consider the seminal emission to be a problem, to be a part
of a זיבה. ziva So מן דאמר man de'amar מעת לעת, me'es
le'es, if you say 24 hours, דייקנא daykana לפנות ערב, lifnos erev,
towards evening. So he has this event at night and all the
way until the next night any seminal emission is going to be
treated like זיבה. ziva ואידך דייקנא מקרה לילה. Ve'idach daykana mikreh layla.
No, only that night itself. By the morning it already won't have
that status. So that's only יומו. yomo. Like יומו yomo meaning here
presumably not the halachic day, but like a 12-hour period, like that
segment of the day.
So, ומן דאמר u'man de'amar ולפנות ערב, velifnos erev, הכתיב מקרה לילה?
hakasiv mikreh layla? But if you say לפנות ערב, lifnos erev, what
do you do with the fact that it says only an event
of the evening? אמר לך: Amar lecha: אורחא דקרא orcha de'kra למקרי
בליליא. limakti baleilya. No, אורחא דקרי. orcha de'keri. Excuse me. No, that's
what happens, that normally seminal emission happens at night, but it does-
but the טומאה tumah of the זיבה ziva that we consider it
to be like a זיבה ziva, goes till the next evening. So
bottom line is what did we say? We're back to what we
said before, that semen from a זב after a person is already
a זב is treated like זיבה ziva, and therefore it is טמא
tamei even by משא. masa. We rejected it initially because we said
well that's only because there are droplets of זיבה ziva, mixed up
in it. It's not because of the semen itself. Which even so
would have been a beautiful read of the משנה, Mishna that's the
whole point of רגלים לדבר. That's why we're treating it like זיבה,
ziva because of רגלים לדבר, because we assume there's other stuff. But
the גמרא Gemara wanted to make it in principle that the semen
is a problem. So it says yeah, actually even if there weren't
droplets of זיבה, ziva based on this פסוק, we learn that the
semen following the זיבה, ziva. either within 24 hours or for that
same period, for a brief period of time, is considered to be
like זיבה ziva itself, and that's what the משנה Mishna. means, that
the semen following it is treated like זיבה itself.
And this whole deliberation, what is it going to have to do
again? Bring us back to like the third ראייה as well. In
other words, this- so there's two things.
One is if it's due to external causes, do we care? After
two ראייה we don't, or maybe after three we don't.
That's- And the semen itself will be a problem and now, again,
that was this deliberation. Exactly. All right, yes.
What is the nature of this... what is the nature of that
material? Is it like some an infection?
Yeah, so the משנה Mishna describes what it looks like. I can
read you the משנה, what exactly it's coming from. Like I said,
there are some people that want to think maybe it's like some
type of a, you know, of a gonorrhea or something like that.
The British,
English
translation of the תלמוד Talmud always say gonorrhea,
gonorrhea.
So how would it relate to weakness of the body then if
it's an infection?
Yeah, I don't know. Meaning I think that it's just that we
don't know that we because maybe we don't know exactly,
you know, the גמרא Gemara never identifies what it's based on. So
it could just be that the גמרא Gemara. basically wants to make
sure that you know it's something. Once it's attributable to something else,
it's sort of like צרעת. Tzaraat. Like you know, we don't want
to assume it's a normal medical condition, like you know, and therefore
if it's attributable to something that's more causal, that specifically makes it
not זיבה. You know what I'm saying? So, but right, because I
think the גמרא Gemara is not taking a like doesn't say oh
it's this condition. It actually wants to make it something. So if
you want to hear if I can quickly find let me see
if I can find the משנה that would say that would describe
what it looks like.
Also, I don't know if that's but there was like a common
idea across a lot of cultures that like seminal emissions weaken you.
Aha. So- No, I understand.
Yeah,
he's talking about the זיבה itself.
It's it's being absent then of these other issues.
But I thought I understood- wait- what?
I thought there was some difference between when things were dry...
There is, there is some- yeah, there is some difference.
Yeah, there is.
I just don't want to get into it.
Hold on, let me just see very quickly if I can't find
another minute.
All right, last משנה. Here we are. And actually a little like
right, a little somewhat aggadic what the גמרא gemara is going to
be aggadic. נזיר היה שמואל כדברי רב נהוראי. Nazir haya Shmuel k'divrei
Rav Nehorai. Right? So שמואל Shmuel was a נזיר, nazir? which is
what רב נהוראי Rav Nehorai says. שנאמר ומורה לא יעלה על ראשו.
She'ne'emar u'mora lo ya'aleh al rosho. Right? It doesn't say- never says
that he will not drink or be מיטמא למתים, mitamei l'meisim, but
it says he will not have a razor come over his head.
So what else is that if not נזירות? nezirut? Of course, and
it's very similar also, right? Because it's his mother talking the same
way it was like-
like שמשון's- Shimshon well שמשון Shimshon it was the angel but talking
to the mother. Anyway, so once again, somebody else imposing it on
the child and the irony being that we've heard before that a
father can make his son a נזיר, nazir, but in these cases
it's always either the mother or the angel, not the father. Anyway,
okay. נאמר בשמשון ומורה ונאמר בשמואל ומורה מה מורה האמור בשמשון נזיר
אף מורה האמור בשמואל נזיר. Ne'emar b'Shimshon u'mora v'ne'emar b'Shmuel u'mora mah
mora ha'amur b'Shimshon nazir af mora ha'amur b'Shmuel nazir. So it's not
enough to say he wasn't going to get his head shaved, because
why would that say he's a נזיר? nazir. That's just one aspect.
But because of the same language used by שמשון, Shimshon, and there
we know he was a נזיר, Nazir, it says נזיר אלהים יהיה
הנער מן הבטן. nazir Elokim yiheyeh hana'ar min habaten. So here too
we assume he was a נזיר. nazir, אמר רבי יוסי: Amar Rabi
Yose: so רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose said back to רב נהוראי, Rav
Nehorai, והלא אין מורא אלא של בשר ודם? v'lo ein mora ela
shel basar vadam? So he says מורא mora means fear, not a
razor. Of course that would be spelled with an אלף. alef. Okay.
But so it says that no he will never be afraid, he'll
never be fearful of any human being. Which is a very funny
way of challenging it.
Okay, so אמר ליה רב נהוראי: Amar lei Rav Nehorai: so רב
נהוראי Rav Nehorai said back,
אמר לו, amar lo, והלא כבר נאמר ויאמר שמואל איך אלך ושמע
שאול והרגני? v'halo kvar ne'emar vayomer Shmuel eich eileich v'shama Shaul va'haragani?
שוכבר היה לו מורא של בשר ודם. Shekvar hayah lo mora shel
basar vadam. You can't say it means he won't be afraid of
people, it's clear he was afraid of people! So that can't be
what it means. I don't know why they don't just say it's
spelled with a הא hey and not an אלף. alef. Anyway, okay.
So what...
yes... I just have a small question, is it unusual for there
to be in a משנה a תנא tanna with an abnormal name?
נהוראי? Nehorai? Yeah, that's interesting, yeah. Also, yeah. I don't know what
to say, that was his name though, but yeah. Okay. אמר ליה
רב חייא לבריה
Amar lei
Rav
Chiyya l'breih so אמר ליה רב לחייא בריה: Amar lei Rav l'Chiyya
breih: so רב said to חייא Chiyya his son, חטוף וברך. chatof
u'varech.
So grab and make a ברכה. bracha. What-
so we'll see what this means,
meaning, but you should be making the ברכה bracha for like you
know for other people, like whether it's a ברכת הנהנין Birkat HaNehenin
or ברכת המזון. Birkat HaMazon. Okay, or ברכה... bircha... it just says
it's ברכה- bircha חטוף... chatof... חטוף כוס של ברכה Chatof kos shel
beracha וברך ברכת זימון, u'varech birchas zimun, okay, is what תוספות, Tosafot,
that's not תוספות, Tosafot, excuse me, that's רש״י, Rashi,
okay. So but anyway, you should be the one to make a
ברכה, bracha, be it Kiddush, whatever it is. וכן אמר ליה רב
הונא לרבה בריה, V'chen amar lei Rav Huna l'Rabbah breih,
חטוף וברך, chatof u'varech, go grab and make the ברכה. bracha. וממרא
דמברך עדיף, u'mimra d'mevarech adif, it sounds like the one making the
ברכה bracha is better? והתניא ve'hanya רבי יוסי Rabi Yose אומר גדול
העונה אמן יותר מן המברך? gadol ha'oneh Amen yoser min hamevarech? It's
better to say אמן Amen than to make the ברכה. bracha. ואמר
ליה... va'amar lei... I can't read this because my גמרא here is...
I know, I know, my גמרא here is... it's like the printing
got all mixed up. Here, I'll just take another גמרא. I got
it, I got it.
Okay, ואמר ליה רב נהוראי. va'amar lei Rav Nehorai. Okay, okay, והתניא
רבי יוסי אומר גדול העונה אמן יותר מן המברך ואמר ליה רב
נהוראי, ve'hanya Rabbi Yosei omer gadol ha'oneh Amen yoser min hamevarech va'amar
lei Rav Nehorai, השמים כך הוא. hashamayim kach hu. Presumably the only
reason we're quoting this, besides that like it's the end of a
מסכת masechet so we might as well do something fun, is presumably
because of רב נהוראי Rav Nehorai because he's a, as Dove pointed
out, very rare name, you know, a תנא, tanna, so here we
have רב נהוראי Rav Nehorai coming up in a ברייתא. And רב
נהוראי Rav Nehorai said, השמים
כך הוא, hashamayim kach hu, by heaven you should know that this
is true, that העונה אמן ha'oneh Amen is better. תדע, teda, you
should know, שרי גוליירים מתגרים במלחמה, she'rei gulyarim misgarim b'milchama, the, of
the, the warriors go out and fight in the war... or not
גוליירים gulyarim actually, I meant to look it up in Jastrow but
I didn't. What does he say גוליירים gulyarim means there on... What?
Unclear. Unclear meaning?
No, the literal meaning is unclear. One Latin for
galiaratus, משמשת אנשי צבא, meshameshet anshei tzava, it's like the... foot soldiers?
The assistant. The light... the light cavalry.
Or a warrior has his...
a knight has his... whatever... Uh-huh.
Right.
Or
weapons bearer.
Might mean the foot soldiers. You send out the foot soldiers to
get slaughtered and then you come in with the cavalry. Common soldiers.
Common soldiers. Okay.
Or yeah, that's right. You first kind of have a skirmish first
to kind of weaken the troops... the defenses and then you send
in the big guns.
The big guns. Okay. וגיבורים נוצחים, v'giborim notzchim, and then the big
guns come in later. So therefore, you know, the guy makes the
ברכה, bracha, that's just the front troops. The אמן, Amen, that's the
power. Now, it's a nice little image, but like the question is,
like what's the logic behind it? Why is the עונה אמן יותר?
oneh Amen yoser? So I gotta tell you, I had this... I
don't know what פשט pshat I gave this גמרא before, but as
I was reading this I was reminded of this great TED Talk.
I think it's the first time I'm quoting a TED Talk here.
Anyway, which talks about the importance of followers. And it actually said,
you know, we always talk about, you know, they have all of
these like you know things for like on leadership and creating the
next generation of leaders or whatever, says we tend to ignore the
importance of followers. So basically it had this amazing video, you've got
to see this, this guy like on a beach and he gets
up, like you know and everybody's just lying on the beach and
this guy starts doing this like totally weird dance. Like everybody's looking
at him like he's nuts, right? So he says he says if
all you have is a leader, like then like you know you
have nothing, like then one guy starts like joining in with him
and doing the whole thing. And then as soon as he starts
getting a follower, all of a sudden it's like he's not in
it alone, he's not crazy, and then that follower gets two other
people start you know so hey, that guy's doing it, they're going
to do it too. This was like not scripted. This was an
actual video, right? And the next thing you know, you've got the
whole section of the beach, everybody is doing it because of all...
so it was a very powerful video. It was like, you know,
it's not just the guy that goes out there and leads. You
don't have the followers then he falls flat. It's the you know
the people that come right after, meaning the first follower that really...
so if a guy just does a ברכה bracha and everybody ignores
it, you know, but you say אמן, Amen, other people say אמן,
Amen, whatever, so it's got a whole starts a whole movement. All
right.
As I was thinking about that, next thing you know we got
a movement, right?
Going to start singing "Alice's Restaurant."
Okay, you'll get the reference some other time.
It's
taking us too long.
So what's the word השמים hashamayim here? But like in God... like
it's like a... like a... an oath? Like in God's name, by
heaven it's so.
So you know the Sephardic practice is when somebody makes a ברכה
bracha on behalf of the community like ספירת העומר Sefirat HaOmer or
the זימון, zimun, the response is השמים. hashamayim. Uh-huh. Right. Interesting. And
so it's a very inter... and it's a similar concept here.
It's the עונה, oneh,
it's the response to the person who's about to make a ברכה,
bracha, this ברכה.
bracha. Right. Interesting. Right. So actually, you know, it's a... Yeah.
It's good. Give it one...
what's he say word for word here? All right. So anyway, and
I really think that that's פשט, pshat, you know, you got one
guy goes out and makes a ברכה, bracha, nobody says anything, it's
just the one guy. You start answering אמן, Amen, you get a
whole backing to it. Okay.
So תנאי היא. tannai hi. So anyway, so why should you run
to make the ברכה? bracha? You should be the first guy to
say אמן. Amen. You should be the first follower, not the leader.
So תנאי היא, tannai hi, it's a debate of תנאים. tannaim. דתניא,
detanya, אחד המברך ואחד העונה אמן במשמע. echad hamevarech v'echad ha'oneh Amen
bamashma.
So whether you make the ברכה, bracha, whether you say אמן, Amen,
it's equally counts. אלא...
you sort of you know you more readily try to become the
be the מברך. mevarech. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar,
so that was the end of that and presumably that was only
quoted because of רב נהוראי. Rav Nehorai. אמר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי
חנינא, Amar Rabbi Elazar amar Rabbi Chanina,
and this seems to have no tie in but a nice way
to end on a little word of אגדתא. Agaddeta. תלמידי חכמים מרבים
שלום בעולם שנאמר וכל בנייך לימודי השם ורב שלום בנייך. Talmidei chachamim
marbim shalom ba'olam shene'emar vechol banayich limudei Hashem verav shalom banayich. All
of your children are learners as students of God and they bring
much peace. הדרן עלך מסכת נזיר Hadran alach masechet Nazir or גמרנו
מסכת נזיר gemarnu masechet Nazir וסליקא לה מסכת נזיר. v'slika la masechet
Nazir.
So I was trying to come up with some way in which
that had something to do with נזיר, nazir. these last two אגדתות,
Agaddetot, but you know they really seem independent. I don't know if
somebody can come up with some smart with some brilliant way to
connect this.
Is there any source where this מימרא meimra continues אל תקרי בנייך
אלא בונייך? al tikri banayich ela bonayich?
Yeah, so if you take a look he says they quote at
the side that it's in the גמרא in ברכות, Berachot, it has
that ending, but I think that scholars believe last time I checked
that that actually is a later gloss, that you don't need to
do like you know that בנייך banayich first it's about שלום, shalom,
רב שלום, rav shalom, and בנייך banayich is always like you know
spiritual heirs or children, you don't have to say בונייך, bonayich, right?
So I don't know but yeah, that
presumably that's a later gloss. But again what this has to do
specifically with נזירות nezirot I don't know. But in case anybody figured
that you finished this מסכת masechet and you don't know bottom line
how to really be a נזיר, so at the end of in
the Vilna Shas at the end of the פירוש המשניות peirush hamishnayot
of the רמב״ם Rambam which occurs right afterwards, there's something here that
they don't know who wrote this, but it
says זאת תורת הנזיר בכה יחטב כסדרן. zos toras hanazir becho yechatev
kesidran. So somebody actually organized so you can either read the רמב״ם
הלכות נזיר Rambam hilchos Nazir or you could read this and you
could know exactly how to be a נזיר. Okay, so we'll see
you all tomorrow for מסכת סוטה. masechet Sotah. How long? I don't
know, just one page. All right.